Guide to the Terry-Slocomb Family Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Terry-Slocomb family papers
1809-1891
MS 483
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
0.75
(2 boxes)
The papers consist of correspondence, a diary, household accounts, and professional documents relating to William Terry; his wife, Maria Roxana Slocomb Terry; his sister, Esther Asenath Terry; and their family and friends in Massachusetts, Connecticut, Pennsylvania, and Minnesota.
Terry family
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Purchased from Whitlock's in 1942.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Scope and Contents
The Terry-Slocomb Family Papers consist mainly of correspondence, the bulk of which is letters addressed to William Terry; his wife, Maria Roxana (Slocomb) Terry; and his sister, Esther Asenath Terry, between 1840 and 189-. They wrote to one another and also received letters from friends and colleagues and from other members of the Terry and Slocomb families in Massachusetts, Connecticut, Pennsylvania, and Minnesota. This is mainly personal correspondence, but the letters of William and Esther include accounts of their experiences as physician and nurse in U.S. Army hospitals during the Civil War, and Esther's later letters describe her work as a teacher in freedmen's schools in Virginia and Georgia and as a missionary among the Jews of New York City. There are also letters ot their father Daniel Terry, from (his brother-in-law?) David Parsons, Harpers Ferry, Virginia, 1817-1821. All the letters are catalogued by sender and recipient in the Union and departmental manuscript catalogues.
The rest of the collection consists of a diary and professional documents of William Terry, household account books of Maria Roxana (Slocomb) Terry, and miscellaneous papers belonging to them and other members of the Terry family.
The Terry-Slocomb Family Papers were purchase from Whitlock's in 1942.
Biographical / Historical
William Terry, son of Daniel and Mary Pease (Parsons) Terry, was born in Sutton, Massachusetts on June 8, 1822. He studied at Amherst College and in 1846 received his M.D. from Pennsylvania College. He practiced in Sutton, Massachusetts until 1860, when he moved to Ansonia, Connecticut. During the Civil War, Terry served as an assistant surgeon in a military hospital in Alexandria, Virginia. He died in 1908. Esther Asenath Terry, sister of William Terry, was born in Enfield, Connecticut on January 24, 1818. She was a nurse in military hispitals during the Civil War, a teacher of freedmen in Virginia and Georgia after the war, and a missionary in New York City. Terry died in Ansonia, Connecticut on November 16, 1880.
African Americans; Education; Families; Freedmen; Jews; Medicine; Women; Ansonia (Conn.); Connecticut; Harpers Ferry (W. Va.); New England; Southern States; Sutton (Mass.); United States -- History -- Civil War, 1861-1865 -- Medical and sanitary affairs; Educators; Missionaries; Nurses; Physicians; Parsons, David, -1872; Terry, Esther Asenath, 1818-1880; Terry, Maria Roxana Slocomb, 1824-; Terry, William, 1822-1908; Slocum family; Terry family
- Inventory
  - Correspondence, 1817-1886 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1887-1891 (Box 2)
  - Maria Roxana (Slocomb) Terry Household account books, 1848-1854 (Box 2)
  - William Terry
    - Certificates of his performance as student and teacher, 1837-1846 (Box 2)
    - Diary, 1841-1867 (Box 2)
    - Tickets of admission to medical lectures and facilities, 1843-1846 (Box 2)
    - List of subscriptions to help him care for the sick and poor, 1870 (Box 2)
  - Legal and financial papers, 1809-1881 (Box 2)
  - Miscellaneous papers, undated (Box 2)
  - Genealogical notes, undated (Box 2)